







VIKAS KUMAR SRIVASTAVA

6940 Sawmill Vill Dr. Columbus OH, 43235 +1-9195907003 vikas.k.srivastava@gmail.com

SUMMARY

An Experienced CCIE Datacenter Engineer, with recognized strength in implementing and supporting advanced Enterprise Datacenters, cloud solutions and applications. Ability to design, troubleshoot and optimize legacy and new datacenter designs. Keen in learning new technologies on my own, current interests include cloud solutions like OpenStack, AWS and SDN, OpenFlow. Successfully maintain complete professionalism and personal commitment with excellent communication and people skills and the ability to train, motivate and supervise a team.

TECHNICAL SKILLS

Data Center Products : Nexus 7000, 5k, 2k, NX-OS, Cisco UCS, Fabric Interconnect, B-Series and C-Series

Servers

Data Center Technologies: OTV, VDC, vPC, Fabric Path, FEX

Cisco Routers Platforms : 3900, 7200 Series

Cisco Switches Platforms : 2900, 3500, 3700, 4500 and 6500 Series, Nexus 1000v, MDS 9216, 9509

Switching Protocols : VTP, STP, MST, VLANs, 802.1q Trunking and Inter VLAN Routing

Routing Protocols : OSPF, EIGRP

Storage Protocols : FC, FCoE, iSCSI, NFS,

Storage : NetApp FAS3240, C-Mode, Cisco Invicta

Services : DNS, DHCP, NTP, HSRP, VRRP,

Virtualisation : VMWare vCenter, ESXi, Citrix XenServer, VMWare View

Monitoring/Management : Cisco DCNM, HP OpenView NNM

Cloud / SDN : AWS, EC2, RedHat OpenStack, Nova networking, Neutron, Nova, Puppet

Mirantis Fuel, OpenvSwitch, OpenFlow, Floodlight, Cisco XNC,

OpenDayLight

Cloud Automation : Cloupia/UCS Director, Cisco Process Orchestrator

Programming/Scripting
Tools
: Shell Scripting
: Wireshark, Mininet

OS : RedHat, Ubuntu, Windows

CERTIFICATIONS AND TRAININGS

- Cloudera Hadoop Administrator Training
- CCIE Datacenter # 43202
- RedHat Certified Engineer (RHCE)
- NetApp Certified Data Administrator (NCDA)
- VMware Certified Professional 5 Data Center Virtualization (VCP5-DCV)
- Cisco Storage Networking Support Specialist
- ITIL v3 Foundations (HP Education) Certified
- Certified Ethical Hacker (CEH) Expired
- Cisco Data Center Support for Unified Computing Specialist (DCUCI)

- Deploying Cisco UCS Invicta
- Trained on Deploying Cisco Process Orchestrator
- Trained on Installing and Deploying Cisco UCS Director
- Implementing EMC VNX
- NetApp Cluster Mode SAN
- Openstack Installation and Administration

EDUCATIONAL QUALIFICATION

Bachelor of Engineering, Information Technology with Honors *Institute of Engineering and Technology, Agra*

Higher Secondary and Senior Secondary Kendriya Vidyalaya Mehsana, Gujarat

WORK EXPERIENCE

Cisco Systems. July 2014 - Till Date

Team Lead - Cisco Cloud Infrastructure Services (Openstack) - USA

Openstack Cloud Admin Team Lead, Supporting Cisco's Openstack Cloud (Cisco Cloud Infrastructure Services)

- Good understanding of cloud computing domain, especially IaaS and PaaS space.
- Supporting Cisco BDaaS offering .
- Experience with deployment, configuration and operations in any or all of OpenStack,
- Deep understanding of Linux networking stack and tools
- Good troubleshooting skills on OpenvSwitch, Neutron.
- Working knowledge of configuration management frameworks (Puppet, Chef), orchestration frameworks and Bare-metal provisioning tools
- Experience with troubleshooting complex Openstack environments.

• Cisco Systems. December 2012 - Till Date

Network Consulting Engineer - Cloud and Managed Services

Tier-2 Data Center Engineer for Cisco's Hosted Voice Architecture of UCaaS and HCS for various high profile clients like RBS, Thomas Cook, Allianz, Gen-I and Ingram Micro.

- Performing Capacity and Release Management on Data Center Front.
- Planning, Design and Implementation of Datacenter Architectures.
- Performing Operations Readiness Testing of the entire Hosted Architecture before a customer goes live.
- Engaging with Cisco Business Unit / Architecture team to evolve and develop the UCaaS Architecture.
- Proactively performing Audits on the deployments in order to ensure smooth operations and compliance.
- Perform Defect analysis on the code which is being planned to be upgraded in the infrastructure and thoroughly test the fine details in the lab before implementing it in production environments.
- Create a fully automated HCS backup solution using Shell Scripts and later on ported the architecture on Cisco Process Orchestrator.
- Ordered, Designed and implemented complete Datacenter lab for CaaS.
- Mentor team on the Datacenter related topics and provide trainings.

• NetApp Inc. December 2011 - December 2012

Technical Marketing Engineer for Flexpod

Responsible for driving the vision of products and technologies in the area of datacenter virtualization Responsible for the cross-collaboration between different product, engineering, sales, and marketing teams which contribute to NetApp's "virtualization" message via Flexpod.

Responsible for writing/validating best practice guides, upgrade validation guides, design guides and technology overviews for distribution among sales teams, customers, partners and analysts.

- Design and Validation of new FlexPod Systems
- Design cloud infrastructure solutions in collaboration with NetApp partners.
- Design, architect and validate storage centric enterprise solutions, by integrating NetApp and partner or third party vendor technologies.
- Accountable for project deliverables working with cross-functional and business unit teams and lead projects within the team.
- Develop technical collateral for best practices guides, design guides, integration guides etc. This includes lab work, technical writing, and revision work.
- Create and present technical presentations to customers and partners, and gather feedback to influence product and solution offerings.
- Tata Consultancy Services. July 2011 November 2011
 System Engineer Cisco Practice

Worked at TCS and provided solution and implementation support to the Cisco Datacenter customers.

Job Responsibilities:

- Study and understand the technical design of Cisco UCS and review the same
- Participate in review meetings involving UCS DC and also help any remote locations to install similar setup
- Responsible for working with the team to provide overall solution involving Virtualization, Storage, Compute, Security and Network.
- Assisting in new service profile creation and server build.
- Installation / Configuration of VMWare Infrastructure including vCenter, ESXi, VUM etc.

Aricent Technologies (Cisco Technical Assistance Center). March 2009 - March 2011 Network Specialist - Datacenter/UC TAC

Worked at Cisco TAC, providing support to all customers worldwide. Providing round-the-clock technical support services, online and over the phone. Handled escalations from the team as and when required. Job Responsibilities:

- Unified Communications and Unified Computing Systems
- Configuring call control protocols on Voice Gateways H.323, MGCP and SIP.
- Installation & Configuration of CCM servers & Voice Gateways
- Coordinating with different Service Providers for Voice trunk connectivity issues
- Troubleshooting DB Replication issues.
- Recreate customer networks for engineering and troubleshooting.
- Packet level troubleshooting experience with Wireshark.
- Assist with physical installation of UCS B / UCS C Series Servers
- Troubleshooting problems related to UCS

United Nations WFP. Dec 2006 - March 2009 ICT Specialist

Globally, the organization has presence in various countries which operate on a private WAN for voice and data Traffic. These corporate services are hosted in Rome in a new custom-built data centre.

Job Responsibilities:

- Technical Support for LAN/WAN Operations
- First level support for equipment, configuration, software related to Voice/WAN connectivity
- First level support for proxies, firewalls as they affect Country Office connectivity, including consulting support for local ICT infrastructure configuration.
- Service monitoring as per procedures supplied.
- Respond to alerts received from monitoring systems

Hobbies: Watching Movies, Learn / Experiment with new upcoming technologies in my home lab.

I hereby declare that the above-mentioned information is correct up to my knowledge and I bear the responsibility for the correctness of the above-mentioned particulars.

Place: Bangalore Vikas Srivastava